Woman's Club of Waco records, Inclusive: 1892-1979, Bulk: 1911-1947
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Woman's Club of Waco records
Inclusive: 1892-1979, Bulk: 1911-1947
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
225
The Woman's Club of Waco
6 document boxes
The [Waco] Woman's Club records contain administrative records and meeting minutes of the organization from 1897—1949, as well as yearbooks and scrapbooks from 1907—1974. Also included are materials related to the Waco Federation of Clubs, and various related organizations.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
The Woman's Club of Waco, an educational and philanthropic club for the women of Waco, was founded on 1892 January 5. While the club began with only eight members, it grew rapidly, and soon included many of the leading women of the city. The club flower was the rose, and the club colors were red and white.
In 1898, the Woman's Club of Waco participated in a meeting that formed a city federation of women's clubs. While the Woman's Club of Waco joined with other city clubs to accomplish common goals, the club has always retained a high degree of autonomy in their activities.
Prominent among the club has been the ideas of self-improvement through education, as shown through their memorable motto: "If I rest, I rust." For much of its history, club members gave presentations on varied topics during monthly meetings. During World War I and II, many of the presentations had to do with the war. During other time periods, presentations included topics of international interest, self-improvement, science, history, finances, among others. Voting rights for women was a topic of intense early interest, with the club signing a petition, along with other clubs, to be forwarded to Washington D.C. in support of voting rights for women.
The club has been involved with efforts to improve the lives of Waco citizens since its founding. During the World Wars, club members visited soldiers at Camp MacArthur weekly, bringing books and food. They led a book drive to furnish the on-base library with books for soldiers, worked closely with the Red Cross to make bandages, and organized a benefit concert for soldiers in Carroll Library Chapel on the campus of Baylor University.
Today, the Woman's Club of Waco continues to provide philanthropic and educational opportunities to the women of the city of Waco.
Scope and Content
The Woman's Club of Waco records include yearbooks, minutes, and some administrative materials related to the educational and philanthropic work of the club in Waco. The minutes and yearbooks series are by far the largest, with voluminous information on the activities of the club through the years. Most of the minutes are handwritten in bound notebooks, and thoroughly document the many activities of the club.
Arrangement
The Woman's Club of Waco records was foldered with titles prior to the current finding aid. There were several existing inventories, but none were completely accurate. Folder titles were mostly retained from the last round of processing.
Currently, the Woman's Club of Waco records includes three series: I. Minutes, II. Yearbooks, and III. Administrative.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 225. Acquired 1971-02-08
Related Resources
Related references
Kelley, Dayton, ed. The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County, Texas. Waco, Texian Press, 1972.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Texas Federation of Women's Clubs.; Waco Federation of Women's Clubs.
Subjects
Women -- Societies and clubs -- Texas -- Waco.; Women -- Texas -- Waco.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Women.
Genres
Minutes (Records); Programs (Publications).; Yearbooks.
- Minutes, 1892-1979; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains the minutes of the Woman's Club of Waco. These minutes document close to one hundred years of philanthropic and educational work in Waco. This series is in good condition.
  - Minutes, 1892-1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1897-1899 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1901-1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1904-1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1905-1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1911-1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1919-1923 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1923-1926 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1929-1931 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Transcripts of Minutes, 1898-1903 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Yearbooks, 1897-1982; 2
  This series contains yearbooks and a scrapbook of the Woman's Club of Waco. The scrapbook contains one photograph and a few newspaper clippings, but most of the scrapbook materials are copies of the yearbooks. It is recommended that, due to preservation concerns, researchers view the yearbooks folders rather than the yearbooks in the scrapbook. This series is in poor condition.
  - Yearbooks, 1901-1903 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Yearbooks, 1904-1907 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Yearbooks, 1908-1911 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Yearbooks, 1912-1915 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Yearbooks, Silver Anniversary, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Yearbooks, 1915-1919 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Yearbooks, 1919-1923 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1925-1928 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Yearbooks, 1928-1931 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Yearbooks, 1931-1933 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Yearbooks, 1933-1935 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Yearbooks, 1935-1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yearbooks, 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Yearbooks, 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Yearbooks, 1941-1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Yearbooks, 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Yearbooks, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Yearbooks, 1950-1953 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Yearbooks, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Yearbooks, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Yearbooks, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Yearbooks, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Yearbooks, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Yearbooks, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Yearbooks, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Yearbooks, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Yearbooks, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Yearbooks, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Yearbooks, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, pages 1-4, 1897-1917 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, pages 5-6, 1901-1906 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, pages 7-8, 1916-1918 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, pages 9-10, 1911-1914 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, pages 11-13, 1906-1909 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, pages 14-15, 1918-1926 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, pages 16-21, 1926-1932 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, pages 22-25, 1934-1942 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook, pages 26-28, 1941-1943 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook, pages 27-29, 1944-1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, pages 30-31, 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, pages 32-33, 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, pages 34-35, 1948-1961 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, pages 36-44, 1903-1966 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, pages 48-52, 1904-1917 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, Loose Materials, 1927-1941 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Administrative, 1908-1967; 3
  This series contains the constitution, a program, and a folder of print jobs that the Woman's Club of Waco had printed. This series is in average condition.
  - Constitution and Program, 1908, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Print jobs, 1926-1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)